<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The garland of a greene vvitte Discouering the constancie of Calipolis. A precious spectacle for wanton wiues, fit to be read of all sorts, if oportunitie serue. Profitable to some, and pleasant to all saue the enuious. By R. Turnar.</title>
            <author>Turner, Richard, poet.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 363:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The garland of a greene vvitte Discouering the constancie of Calipolis. A precious spectacle for wanton wiues, fit to be read of all sorts, if oportunitie serue. Profitable to some, and pleasant to all saue the enuious. By R. Turnar.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Richard, poet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Roberts] for William Kirkham, and are to be solde at the little north doore of S. Paules Church, at the signe of the black Boy,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1595?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ (-E4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:1"/>
            <p>THE Garland of a greene Witte. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Diſcouering the conſtancie of <hi>Calipolis.</hi> A precious ſpectacle for wanton Wiues, fit to be read of all ſorts, if oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſerue. Profitable to ſome, and pleaſant to all ſaue the enuious. By <hi>R. Turnar.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Tout ce qui luict ne pas ore.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed for William Kirkham, and are to be ſolde at the little North doore of S. Paules Church, at the ſigne of the black Boy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:2"/>
            <head>To his approoued good friend Maiſter <hi>Iohn Short, R. Turnar</hi> wiſheth health.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinking my worke as ſafe vnder your Patronage from carping, as Vliſſes vnder the ſhield of Aiax, I haue entered my barraine Garden, and there gathered ſuch greene flowers as ſo ſmall a plotte affoordes: and becauſe of the Spring-time I haue made them in a Graland, according to my promiſe to preſent you withall. Pardon my bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that buds but in Sommer with the Mulberie, for I am one of thoſe Poets that came to Homers baſon, to lap vp that hee dooth caſt vp. It ſufficeth me to be a water bough, not a top bud, ſo I may be of the ſame roote: to be yron, not ſteele, ſo I be of the ſame blade: Vinegar, not VVine, ſo I be of the ſame caske: to grinde colours for Apelles, though I can not garniſh. I haue aduentured with the young VVreſtler at the games of Olimpus to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a fall, or at leaſt a foile; if I be pricked with a bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Ile thruſt my hand into the whole buſh. VVhen Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephalus was paynted, Apelles craued but the iudgment of Alexander, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iupiter was carued, Priſsius asked the cenſure of none but Liſippus; neither greatly craue I any but one, the Patroner of my pamphlet. Momus muſt mocke, the Serpent Porphirius is full of poyſon, yet
<pb facs="tcp:11812:3"/> hurteth hee none but himſelfe: the Hearbe Moly hath a flower as white as Snow, but a roote as blacke as Inke: the Palme-perſian Fig-tree, beareth as well Apples as Figs: the Eaſterly winde maketh the bloſſomes to blaſt, and the buddes to blow, the Bee carrieth honey in her mouth, and a ſting in her tayle: ſome diſcloſe ſubtill ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, that are the Authors of the ſame, and in touching others take themſelues by the elboe. But the ſaying is, (Little ſayd is ſoone amended,) Ile keepe a meane, and medle with no man, and though I be kiſſed with Hipar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chion, or forbidden to ſell wine with the Vintner in Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, I will aduenture to put forth a Garland, &amp; thoſe that loue wines will commend my good will. Thus reſting at his liking to whom I preſent my Garland, I end, reſting at his commaund.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:3"/>
            <head>To the curteous Readers.</head>
            <p>GEntle Readers, miſconſter not my writing, as the Schollers did Theodorus, father cenſure aright then raſhly, tis but a Garland, and though ſome flowers be ſweete, looke not that all ſhould haue the like ſauour: weedes are glorious, and perhaps ouer-ſight hath tyed them in my Garland, crop where you like, and carpe not at thoſe you leaue, for the leaſt in value will comprehend the Gardinaries labour. Account not cheeſe chaulk, becauſe both are white, nor the full Moone, a meſſe of curds, leaſt I think of you, as thoſe curſt curres that bark at all but their friends, ſnatching vp bones in open ſtreets, and eating them madly in ſecret corners. The ſharp winds pierce ſubtiller in narrow Lanes, then in open Fields, but ſith I haue no authority to bridle their tongues, nor reaſon in them to rule their owne talke, I am contented to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their taunts: requeſting thoſe my fauorites, to take my Garland friendly, and when my Garden is full of ſweete flowers, ile pluck out the weeds, and place them in my Garland.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours <hi>R. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:4"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>I</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>In chiefeſt time of Sommers ſpring,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>O</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Our Gardens then we make,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>H</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Hearing how cherping Birds doe ſing,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>N</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>No pleaſure els we take.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>S</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>So hauing ſet but ſundry ſprinks,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>H</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Hearbs flowers in their kind,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>O</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Of friendſhip had my Muſe ſtill thinks,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>R</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Reaſon driue it in my mind.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>T</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>This Garland then I made with flowers,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>E</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Each branch ſprung vp with Aprill ſhowers.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="romance">
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:4"/>
            <head>Conſtant Calipolis of FRAVNCE. (⸪)</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the dayes when <hi>Lewis</hi> ſwayed the Scepter of Fraunce, ruled in great pompe and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a man ingenious, ful of valencie, wearing with <hi>Pallas</hi> both the Launce and the Bay. Which <hi>Lewis</hi> continued long time in mortall warres with <hi>Frederick</hi> King of Denmarke, which enuie continued the ſpace of twentie yeeres, in which time, many bloody ſtratagems were perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: ſo time that tryes all things ſo weakened theyr forces, and impaired their furniture, the want of which, draue them to conclude a league for certaine yeeres, with which Ile reſt, and come ſome-what bréefer to the matter.</p>
            <p>In thoſe dayes, in the Citty of <hi>Paris</hi> dwelt a rich Merchant, named <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> who had to wife <hi>Calipolis,</hi> a woman for beauty ſurpaſſing all, becauſe none ſo beautiful, and not ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie adorned with Natures works, as richly graced with <hi>Venus</hi> amorites: ſo beautified with the gifts of both, that Nature her ſelfe bluſhed at the beautie of her owne workes, hayre like the golden wier, Iuory browes, cheekes ſtained with Vermilion tinckture, eyes like the Lampes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> guides the heauenly Sphere, or lightens <hi>Luna</hi> to her ſiluerd Couch: lips like the Cherrie in his chiefeſt prime, a necke like the Lillies on the banks of <hi>Po,</hi> or icie hayre that growes on <hi>Boreas</hi> chinne: her pretty paps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble
<pb facs="tcp:11812:5"/> Chriſt all knobs, or Egypts fountaines that ouer-flowes with milke, a body were it framed of Virgins waxe, by all the cunningſt Artiſts of the world: a belly white and ſoft, much like the Downe vpon thoſe Swans that on <hi>Meander</hi> ſwims, her legge and foote with <hi>Venus</hi> might compare: and to be briefe, for beauty ſuch a one, as would force <hi>Troyalus</hi> to be trothleſſe. Therefore meruaile not, for loue reſpects no difference of ſtate ſo beauty ſerue to ſtirre affection, <hi>Cupid</hi> ſhootes as well at a rag as a robe, the mightieſt Potentates vailes their colours where <hi>Cupid</hi> comes in place, and yéeldeth at his commaund without controle. But ſetting a ſide theſe vaine ambages, it fortuned one <hi>Solinar</hi> a young Gentleman walking in the ſtréete, chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to glaunce his eyes vpon <hi>Calipolis,</hi> and in ſuch ſort, that <hi>Cupid</hi> lying in ambuſh catched him in his clawes, and made him not onely penſiue but paſſionate, and ſo perplexed with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine ſelfe conceit, that he had much adoe to quaile the extreame heate that loues flames had kindled in his breaſt, ſo with the Salamander (bathing in <hi>Aetnas</hi> flames) he haſted to his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and there ſolitarily hauing none but the walls to witnes, his woe, he broke foorth, fetching a heauy ſigh in this manner. Vnfortunate <hi>Solinar</hi> becauſe vnfortunate in thy loue, hadeſt thou perriſhed at thy birth, or beene ſtifled in thy ſwadling clothes, (the Fates had domed thee with deſert,) for nowe growne to ripe yeeres, thou féeleſt more miſeries then thou haſt liued mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. A loue, the laborinth that leadeth men to worſer danger then the Minator in Gréece, or newes of death vnto a damned man, infortuned loue that kindleth deſire, yet affoordeth no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, inconſtant <hi>Venus,</hi> whoſe lawes are tyrranies, whoſe fauors miſfortunes, ſtrumpet as thou art, I diſdaine to call thée Goddeſſe, thou and the baſtard brat thy ſonne, now ſhow your power, your deity, and take reuenge on me, for how ere your colours be, my calamities cannot be more: and merciles wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whoſe faces are lures, whoſe beauties are baytes, whoſe lookes are nets, whoſe words are charmes, and all to bring men vnto ruine, and laſt yet moſt, <hi>Calipolis,</hi> borne of a Tigar, nurſed of the Wolfes in Siria, beautifull yet ouer baſe, fayre,
<pb facs="tcp:11812:5"/> but vnfit, louely yet not to be loued of <hi>Solinar.</hi> Thus rowing in the tempeſtious ſeas of his appetites, guided by a Marriner, that delights in the ſhipwrack of thoſe hee carrieth, perplexed with a thouſand cogitations, ſo extreame was the force of loue, and the ſparks ſo cruell, that patience could not extinguiſh the vaparous heate, nor ſalt teares quench the fiery flames, that wanton loue had kindled in his breaſt.</p>
            <p>So on the ſuddaine he betooke him to his couch, in hope that ſléepe would haue qualified his newe come paſſions. So laying his head vpon the carefull pyllow, intending to nod, his head fell to hammering another matter, plotting a ſecrete meanes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his new come loue: ſo reſtleſſe, turning from ſide to ſide, though his bones aked not, his head was bruſed, and his wits were a wooll gathering. Thus tumbling no long ſpace on the reſtleſſe pillow, but vp he got, and taking his Lute, firſt framed out ſome dolefull tune, and hauing fitted his purpoſe, he fingered his pen, and in a perplexed humor he writ this ditty.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <head>Solinars Dittie.</head>
                        <l>LIngering in loue and like to die,</l>
                        <l>hey ho, hey ho, my poore hart,</l>
                        <l>I freeze amaine, and yet I fry,</l>
                        <l>Now fie vpon this extreame ſmart.</l>
                        <l>What pleaſing paines is paltry loue,</l>
                        <l>hey ho, hey ho, thats my greefe,</l>
                        <l>I ſtill condemne but neuer proue,</l>
                        <l>a froward way to finde releefe.</l>
                        <l>Delight prognoſticates my death,</l>
                        <l>hey ho, hey ho, woe is mee,</l>
                        <l>Pangs doe ſtop my vitall breath,</l>
                        <l>comfort is fled, no ioy I ſee.</l>
                        <l>Accurſed were mine eyes to gaze,</l>
                        <l>hey ho, hey ho, worſe lucke mine,</l>
                        <l>Her beauty made mee ſtand amaze,</l>
                        <l>ſo gay did glaunce her glorious eyne.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11812:6"/>
                        <l>Vpon her browes did Venus play,</l>
                        <l>hey ho, hey ho, Mars did cry,</l>
                        <l>If poult foote Vulcan were away,</l>
                        <l>then Mars in loue would make a try.</l>
                        <l>But Vulcan lay ſlumbring on her lap,</l>
                        <l>hey ho, hey ho, blacke is he,</l>
                        <l>Could I but catch her in a trap,</l>
                        <l>full ſure tormented Vulcan ſhould be,</l>
                        <l>For he is blacke, and would become,</l>
                        <l>hey ho, hey ho, the Cuckolds horne,</l>
                        <l>Tis quickly ſaid, but were it done,</l>
                        <l>Venus would the Black-ſmith ſcorne.</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Hauing finiſhed this Ditty, and finding opportunitie as the ſaying is, The Cat béeing away, the Mouſe will play, hee ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelfe vnder her Chamber window, and ſo warbled foorth this Ditty. The ſiluer ſtrings of the Lute was ſo heauenly, that the eccho of the ſwéet ſounde, awaked the Saint from her ſléepe, and mounting from her night couch, opened the caſement, and vttered theſe words. What ſweete melodious tunes are theſe, that ecchoes ſweet harmony to my dying ſoule? Ah ſay ſweete hapleſſe friende, whats cauſe of all your dolefull tunes? Mee thinkes they increaſe a ſecond heauen in my hart, then bluſh not man, take courage and comfort your ſelfe, and if your helpe bee in mine hands, aſſure your ſelfe to obtaine ſalue for your ſore, be it no impeach to my honeſt name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solinar</hi> ouercloyed with ioyes at the fauourable words vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Calipolis,</hi> fetching a heauie ſigh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the center of his hart, curtained his face with a ſuddaine bluſh, and replied in this ſort. Farre be it from my hart to think of ſuch baſe vilanies, as might in queſtion Lady call your name, yet is the matter of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, ſtanding vpon the credite of my ſtate, too affected with zeale and ſecrecie, as ſhould I ſpeake and faile in my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it would redownd greatly to my preiudice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calipolis,</hi> knew by the ſhoe, where the foote was pinched, for loue cannot be hidden, day appeares at little holes, and the leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:11812:6"/> ſparke of wilde fire, ſetteth a houſe on flame. The ſting of loue, woundeth deadly to the hart, therefore ſhee encouraged him in this manner, fayning as though ſhe perceiued nothing. Sweete friend, if the cauſe of your complaints be according to the tennor of your proteſtations, aſſure your ſelfe to receiue comfort to your owne content, and to pacifie your paſſions with pleaſant ioy: therefore frolike in thine attempt, ſpeake thy fill, &amp; if thou faile in thy deſire, imagin I am either too coy, or thy ſelfe too curious.</p>
            <p>Shee, hauing vttered theſe wordes, <hi>Solinar</hi> in breefe began to breathe out his paſſions, but Fortune (who is conſtant in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vnconſtancie, alwaies inclined to croſſe mens cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,) did breake them from their chat in this manner. <hi>Baltegar</hi> one that had beene of long continuance a friendly fauorite to <hi>Calipolis,</hi> Fortune ſo ſpightfully thwarted his endeuours, that he could neuer obtaine perſonally to ſpeake to her, til the Fates had plotted this time and place of opportunitie: and finding <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linar</hi> ſo conuerſant with her, he ſo highly fauoured, (Loue that Tyrant ſo ſtirred his ſtomack, that hardly coulde hee holde his hands from murther,) yet at laſt he began in this manner.</p>
            <p>Preſumptious <hi>Solinar,</hi> whoſe peremtory attempts deſerues the gurdon of death, dareſt thou preſume to court that Saint in whom I haue ſhrined my hart, the Goddeſſe whom I adore, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting of her as my ſecond ſelfe, therefore hands of, or els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy death, drawing his ponyard. Theſe hard euents ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed <hi>Solinar</hi> greatly, yet putting on good courage, he replyed to this effect. Good ſir (quoth he) are you priuiledged in loue, or ſo tied to the beauty of a woman, that no man may looke vpon her but your ſelfe: had the Gods fauoured me with ſuch a priuiledge I durſt aduenture without requeſt to ſhew it.</p>
            <p>To this replied <hi>Baltegar,</hi> ſuffiſeth beauty is my priuiledge, if that ſuffiſe not inquiſitiue <hi>Solinar</hi> heere is my weapon to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe it. With that <hi>Calipolis</hi> as one amazed at theſe hard e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents, beeing a woman ſo conſtant, as no <hi>Circes</hi> with all her charines, nor <hi>Calipſoes</hi> inchantments, could once preuaile a iote to blemiſh her affection, ſhée was conſtant <hi>Silera,</hi> and not a diſſembling <hi>Helin,</hi> ſhée eſtéemed more of an ounce of honeſtie
<pb facs="tcp:11812:7"/> then a pound of paltry ſtuffe: ſo wrincking her browes, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying her face with an angry bluſh, beganne in thys manner. What meanes theſe vaine ambages? tis not vnknowne to the better of you both, that <hi>Calipolis</hi> is trothed Spouſe to <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramet,</hi> and ſuch a one, as ſcornes to ſtaine her marriage rites with ſuch baſe reproch, or the vertue of an honeſt name, with the infamous ſlaunder of a naughty Packe, or a wonder to the worlds ſole eye. <hi>Baltager</hi> impatient to heare her prattle, enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by loue, broke forth into theſe ſpeeches. Miſtreſſe (quoth he) fayre <hi>Helens</hi> nuptials of Greece were ſolemnized, yet prooued ſhee vnconſtant to <hi>Menelaus,</hi> and forſooke the delicates of <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> and what enforced that but loue. Admit ſhe did, ſayd <hi>Calipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> yet haue I vowed my ſelfe to the contrary, as conſtant to my <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> as euer that fayre <hi>Dido</hi> was to her <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> and rather ſhall the running ſtreames of <hi>Exanthoes</hi> recoyle, or the world turne to a Chaos, whence it came, then will <hi>Calipolis</hi> once falcifie her faith to <hi>Mountgramet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solinar</hi> frying in loue, like the Salamander in <hi>Aetnas</hi> flames, taking her by the hand, beganne as followeth. By your leaue Miſtris, giue me leaue to reply, Windes often vary, and who reſembles them but women? <hi>Baltager</hi> breathing it out like a Braggart, thus ſaid, Sirra, who gaue you authoritie to make compariſons? twere not amiſſe to make thee eate thy words, or with my ponyard thruſt them downe thy throate.</p>
            <p>Whilſt thus they were at controuerſie trying each others ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in loue, <hi>Fredericke</hi> King of Denmarke, being lately come to the Court of Fraunce, accompanied with King <hi>Lewis,</hi> fortuned to behold this heauie aſpect, wondring what it ſhould progneſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, inſomuch that entring ſomewhat neerer, King <hi>Lewis</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in this manner. Baſe peſants, auoyde our preſence, and get you packing. With that they both departed with mickle ſorrow, fetching many a heauy ſight, but marke what after happened. Loue that reſpects no difference of ſtate, kinled ſuch flames in <hi>Fredericks</hi> breaſt, that hanging downe his heade towards the earth, not a merry word for a million, he ſtood all a mort. Then <hi>Lewis,</hi> whoſe loue did ballance <hi>Fredericks</hi> affection, plucking vp
<pb facs="tcp:11812:7"/> a ſmall courage from a conquered hart, taking <hi>Frederick</hi> by the hand, fell to theſe words.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes (my Lord) the blinded boy hath played the wagge with you, in loue at the firſt looke, if he haue eſcaped <hi>Lewis,</hi> thou art ſtung. Can beautie bring you to ſuch a bane, that is but a bauin blaſt? <hi>Hebay</hi> bloſſoms, that open with the dew, and ſhut with the ſunne, Roſes garded with prickles, flowers ſubiect to the Northerne blaſts, the beautifull bloſſoms in <hi>Parthia,</hi> that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in their prime, or the apples of <hi>Tantalus,</hi> that touched turne to aſhes: the comly ſkinne, that clothes the hatefull Snake, the Box tree, whoſe leafes are alwaies gréene, and the ſeedes poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: abolliſh this fond determination, extend the Tyrant out by force, for entring at the eye, it harbors at the hart, loue is more perrilous then precious, affording delight with deſire, but death with deniall. <hi>Lewis</hi> beeing wringed with the ſame ſhoe, was preſently ſtrooke with a contrary obiect, in thys manner, <hi>In a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour il ny ade fauta,</hi> why rage I beyond reaſon, ſhe is beautiful and therefore worthy to be loued, ſhée is comely, and deſerues to be accounted on. How now <hi>Lewis,</hi> hath loue turned thy launce to a Poets penne, to paynt out thy paſſions, is Armour turned to amor? What? is <hi>Mars</hi> able to reſiſt <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and not to with ſtand beauty? is it <hi>Venus</hi> muſt were the Target, and <hi>Mars</hi> the diſtaffe? <hi>Omphale</hi> handle the Club, and <hi>Hercules</hi> the Spindell? muſt <hi>Alexander</hi> crouch, and <hi>Campaſpe</hi> looke coy? this verifies the old prouerbe to be true, women will rule in loue, howe euer men are luſtie in courage, no dignitie is able to reſiſt <hi>Cupids</hi> deitie. Loue enters by ſeeing women, and works not by hearing their words: therefore ſeeing <hi>Cupid</hi> muſt be obeyed, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to bow: <hi>Nullis herbis amor eſt medicabilis.</hi> So fetching a ſigh, began to ſay, my Lord, there is one thing on the ſuddaine greatly troubles me, which is this, that both you and I ſhoulde ioyne our harts in ſuch vnlooked for paſſions. Not ſo my Lorde ſayd <hi>Fredericke,</hi> I hope you doe but ieſt. Ieſt (ſaid he) nay would I did, then were my griefes the leſſe. Nere grieue my Lorde, (quoth <hi>Frederick,</hi>) for ſith the cauſe is ſuch to ioyne our harts in ſuch a ſimpathy, all enuy ſet aſide, let vs agree to yeelde to each
<pb facs="tcp:11812:8"/> others fortune in our choyce. Content ſayde <hi>Lewis</hi> and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo ere befall, ſhake handes my Lorde, and Fortune thriue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all.</p>
            <p>Thus after much prattle, they concluded that <hi>Lewis</hi> ſhould giue her the firſt onſet, who taking her by the hand, beganne as followeth: Miſtres of my harts ſole affection, brighter then ſiluered <hi>Luna</hi> or <hi>Sol,</hi> amidſt his Horizon, ſhee whom the Gods hath appointed to ranſack my entralls and robed me of my hart, it were enleſſe to rehearſe the inward griefe I haue ſuſtayned, ſince I fixed mine eyes on that admirable Comet, whoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull rayes, ſtaineth ſtately <hi>Iuno</hi> in <hi>Samos,</hi> or <hi>Diana</hi> in <hi>Delos, Minerua</hi> in <hi>Athens.</hi> It were vaine to boaſt of <hi>Sibillas</hi> beautie, or Egipts fayre <hi>Iſius, Caſſandra</hi> Troyans pride, bright <hi>Penelope,</hi> or Romiſh <hi>Cornelia. Sabo</hi> ſhunne to ſhewe thy face, <hi>Lucrecia</hi> lurke, <hi>Hebe</hi> bluſh, <hi>Sephronia</hi> ſtoope, <hi>Sapho</hi> knéele, and <hi>Laura</hi> yéeld the pride of beauty to this blazing lampe, whoſe rayes hath kinled fire in my breaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calipolis</hi> hauing liſtened to the Syrens ſong, and cloyed her eares with the praiſes of her beautie, armouring herſelfe with the plated coate of conſtancie, in this maner broke him from his vaine ſimilitudes. I beſéech your Maieſtie, if the earneſt entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a poore Merchants wife, may molifie your hart, or the teares of a conſtant Spouſe, may deſire your fauour, (vpon my knées) grant me liberty to ſpeake, for a womans tongue is her beſt defence (quoth ſhe.) <hi>Lewis</hi> that was ſo ſtung with loue, that had ſhe aſked his Diademe, it could not haue béene denied, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her liberty, who framed her ſpéech in this ſort. Dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, the ſcandaliſt reproch that can befall a woman, is to bée ſtayned with the infamous blotte of diſloyaltie, and more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to me is the newes of death, then the name of Concubine to a King, were it the Monarch of the world, and more (quoth ſhée) what might <hi>Mountgramet</hi> thinke of mée, how would the Quéene your bedde-mate looke on mée, to ſee a Peſant borne, poſſeſſe the place of a Princes. Pardon dread King, your requeſt extends to ſuch defamation, that I rather deſire death, then lyfe if it ſtand not with your liking, vnleſſe you extinguiſh this laciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:11812:8"/> loue, and ſet me at liberty.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Lewis</hi> being impatient, becauſe perplexed in minde, to heare ſuch a cooling carde, began as followeth. Heauenly <hi>Iuno</hi> (quoth he) <hi>Dianas</hi> branch, fedde with <hi>Pallas</hi> paps, it forceth not what <hi>Iſabella</hi> ſaith, what <hi>Mountgramet</hi> coniectures, <hi>Lewis</hi> is a King and may commaund, and more to requite thy loue, if <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella</hi> die, Ile gyrt thy temples with a Diadem, brighter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the morning ſtarre, more precious then the Carcanet, the Emerald, Rubie, or the Carbuncle, the Onix, Saphir, and the Chriſtolet, the Topace, Iaſper, and the Adamant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calipolis</hi> not reſpecting theſe large proffers, cut him of in this manner: quoth ſhe who liues to weare a dead mans ſhooes, (I haue heard it ſaide) may gaule his féete with going bare-foote. <hi>Lewis</hi> replied, admit (ſayd he) I make thée Quéene, and baniſh <hi>Iſabella.</hi> I, ſayd ſhe, ſo to gaine a Crowne, might heape a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand cares vpon my head, therefore ſwéete Prince, quoth ſhée, were it to beare <hi>Atlas</hi> burden on my backe, to roule the reſtleſſe ſtone with <hi>Siciphus,</hi> I would reſt at your commaund, rather then to impeach my honeſt name with any title of defamation. <hi>Lewis</hi> ſéeing neither ſpéech nor proffers would preuaile, gaue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with a kinde ſalute, hoping in time to attaine the top of his deſire. With that <hi>Calipolis</hi> dooing her dutie, departed. All this while ſtoode <hi>Fredericke</hi> in a paſſionate dumpe, not able to vtter a word for a world of wealth. After her depart hee began as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: How farre hath nature wrought beyond her ſkill, in framing ſuch a Saint, as all the Artiſts in the world cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion? <hi>Apelles</hi> nere pictured the like in Gréece, though <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> did him ſo commend. <hi>Timantes</hi> counterfeits are counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite to this. <hi>Liſippus</hi> ſkill cannot preuaile a iote, <hi>Pigmalion</hi> would haue loued the ſhadow of thys Saint. <hi>Perillis</hi> adored the grounde ſhée goes vpon, and <hi>Alexander</hi> honoured, farre aboue the counterfeit of <hi>Campaſpe.</hi> After he had thus warbled foorth a multitude of prayſes, they both conſented to return to the Court, <hi>Lewis</hi> béeing paſſionate, entred his Chamber of Preſence, but <hi>Fredericke</hi> frying in loues vnquenchable flame, made returne to finde out the Merchant, and méeting him where time and place
<pb facs="tcp:11812:9"/> gaue oportunity, he broke forth into theſe ſpeeches: <hi>Mountgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> quoth he, what is the greateſt ſcandall belonging vnto a married man? <hi>Mountgramet</hi> amazed wherfore the King ſhould vtter ſuch ſpeeches, replyed in this maner: ſith your grace doth permit me liberty to ſpeake, (may it ſtande with your gracious liking) in my conceit, the greateſt ſcandall can befall a man, is to haue his wife play falſe. True, ſaid the King, and it greeueth me, thy ſelfe art tainted with the ſame, and to ſhew thee further teſtis, looke in this glaſſe, in which thou mayſt behold <hi>Calipolis,</hi> and two contending who firſt ſhall graffe the horne.</p>
            <p>After King <hi>Lewis</hi> had ſhewed this ſame by Magicke ſpells, he departed, leauing <hi>Mountgramet</hi> murmuring at his wiues diſloyaltie, who fell to theſe ſpeeches. Ah <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> ſtab thy ſelfe to end thy griefe, griefe newe begunne, nowe gins my hart to faynt. Ah <hi>Calipolis,</hi> vnconſtant <hi>Calipolis,</hi> I alwayes thought thee true, till now the proofe too apparantly is made. Who might for beauty once haue bragged with mee? <hi>Calipolis</hi> exceeded all in beauties brightnes, til now that Lampe is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with inconſtancie. <hi>Phoebus</hi> beames are eclipſed with win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtormes, ſiluered <hi>Luna</hi> is curtained with an obſcure clowde, the prickles hath ouer-ſprung the Roſe, the Iuory Lilly turned from rareſt white to Rauens black. And to bee briefe, <hi>Dianas</hi> chaſtitie, is ſtained with diſloialtie. Ah how I proue the ſaying true, The hollow Tree is a hiue for the Hornet, Bées haue ſtings, Fountaines haue Toades, and on the greeneſt trées are Caterpillers found: the Siren ſweetly ſings y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saylers wrack, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Crocodile the Fiſhers woe, the Hienna when ſhe mournes,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen moſt guilefull, the Tygar is cruell, although hee hides his clawes.</p>
            <p>Vnconſtant <hi>Calipolis,</hi> the glory of whoſe face deckt with a vermillion bluſh, did firſt tranſ-forme mine adamant eyes to amorous loue, in conceit ſtayning <hi>Venus</hi> for beautie, beeing much fayrer, and <hi>Pallas</hi> for wiſedome, beeing more wittie, but nowe ſhee hath prooued herſelfe as neere <hi>Pallas</hi> in witte, as <hi>Vulcan Mars</hi> in property, and as farre from <hi>Venus</hi> in beautie, as <hi>Baucis Iuno</hi> in maieſtie. And to conclude, in quantitie ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:11812:9"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſembled the Camelion: héerein the olde Prouerb is am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lified, Euery <hi>Venus</hi> hath her temple, and well may <hi>Vulcan</hi> mock, but <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall enter in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mountgramet</hi> impatient at this hard aſpect, could not paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe, but proteſted that death ſhould guerdon her miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déedes. So calling out one <hi>Anthony,</hi> after many teares hée vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered theſe words: <hi>Anthony,</hi> knowing thée to be a faythfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and ſuch a one as within whoſe breaſt I may ſhroude my ſecrets, I will the bolder participate the ſumme of all, which tendeth to this effect. <hi>Anthony</hi> (quoth he) the Scaraba flyes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer many a ſwéet flower, and lights on a Cowſhard: it is the cuſtome of the flye, to leaue the ſound place of the horſe, and pick at the botch, the manner of Coloquintida to drawe the worſt humours to it ſelfe, the order of Swine to forſake the faire fields and wallowe in the myre: euen ſo did I in my youth, forſake many conſtant <hi>Silerias,</hi> and made choyce of a diſſembling <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maphon,</hi> who hath playde with me as the deceitfull Phiſition doth, in giuing ſwéet ſirrops to make his poyſon goe downe the ſmoother. The Iuglar caſteth a miſt before mens eyes, to doe his ſleights the cloſer, the Sirens ſong is the Saylers wracke, the Fowlers whiſtle the birds death, the wholeſome bayte the Fiſhes bane, the Harpies haue virgines faces, the Vultures ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, Hienna ſpeakes like a friend, and deuoures like a foe, the calmeſt ſeas hides dangerous rocks, the Woolfe iets in Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fells, who would haue thought <hi>Epius</hi> horſe, ſhould haue harboured the deſtruction of Troy? the Sepulcher <hi>Simiramis</hi> whoſe tytle promiſeth wealth to the Kings of Perſia, and is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but rotten bones, the golden ball that <hi>Nero</hi> did conſecrate to <hi>Iupiter, Captolinus</hi> ſtuffed with the ſhauings of his beard. Imagine with thy ſelfe <hi>Anthony,</hi> is not this <hi>Circes</hi> cup, able to turne a reaſonable creature to a brute beaſt: the fact is odious, and therefore vnpardonable, and to be briefe, death ſhall quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance her miſdéeds. And thus to haue it brought cloſely to paſſe, thou ſhalt accompany her thy ſelfe, to Silia my Minor houſe, there when thou haſt her, in thoſe craggy Woods where heapes of trees may hide ſo foule a deede, there cut her ſhort from life.
<pb facs="tcp:11812:10"/> From life, nay let her liue, perhaps ſhe may recant, recant, no, often haue I heard it ſayd, Bred in the bone, will neuer out of the fleſh. Therefore reſolue thy ſelfe, ſhe ſhall dye. With that <hi>Anthony</hi> hearing his Mayſters reſolution, beganne in thys manner.</p>
            <p>Good Maiſter (quoth hee) there is no ſtone ſo hard, but rayne in time dooth pierce, therefore pardon the firſt fault, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh not the branch in his pryme, blaſt not the bud beeing ready to bloſſome, no doubt but good counſell may cauſe ſuch a recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as no Northeren blaſh whatſoeuer, can once blemiſh the beauty of that branch: the Camelion will turne to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, ſo ſhall you not onely liue in content, but receaue ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary comfort, as your ſelfe can wiſh, or in any wiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue.</p>
            <p>This friendly ſaying of <hi>Anthony,</hi> could nothing allay the rancor ſetled in his breaſt, but hee brake foorth in this manner. The common people often times, are more afrayd of the ſerpent that is hidden in the graſſe, then the wilde beaſt that openly feedes vpon the Mountaynes: the Marriner is more endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by priuy ſhe liues, then knowne rocks, the Souldier ſooner killed with a ſmall bullet, then a long ſword, there is more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill in cloſe Fiſtulaes then outward ſores, in ſecrete ambuſhes, then maine battels, in vndermining then in playne aſſaulting, in friends then foes, in ciuill diſcord then forraine warres. But tuſh, tall Cedars from little graines ſhall ſhutte high, great Oakes from ſlender rootes ſpread wide, large ſtreames from narrow ſprings runne farre. One little ſparke fiers a whole Citty, one dram of <hi>Eliborus,</hi> doth ranſack euery vaine, the fiſh <hi>Remora,</hi> hath a ſmall body and great force to ſtay ſhips againſt wind or tide. <hi>Ichnemon,</hi> a little worme, ouer-comes the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant: the Viper ſlayes the Bull, the Weaſell the Cockatrice, and the weakeſt Waſpe ſtingeth the ſtouteſt man of war. The height of heauen is taken by the ſtaffe, the bottome of the Sea, ſounded with lead, the fartheſt Coaſt diſcouered by Compaſſe, the ſecrets of Nature ſearched by wit, the Anatomy of man, ſet out by experience, and the abuſes of women diſcouered by their
<pb facs="tcp:11812:10"/> diſſembling: therefore reſolue thy ſelfe, <hi>Calipolis</hi> ſhall dye, ile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Author, to deuiſe her death, &amp; thou the factour to performe the déede.</p>
            <p>Maiſter, quoth <hi>Anthony,</hi> I knowe women in qualities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mble an arrow, which getting liberty, with wings is carried beyond our reach, kept in the Quiuer, it is ſtill at commaund, or a dog, let him ſlip, and he is ſtraight out of ſight, but hold him in a leaſe, and hee neuer ſtirres, or a Colt, giue him the bridle, and he flings at liberty, but rane him hard, and you may rule him, or a ſhyp, hoyſe the ſayles and it runnes on head, let fall the Anchor and all is well. He runnes farre that neuer turnes, and a fault pardoned, procures the offender from working diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. All theſe ſimilitudes, mixed with ſighes &amp; ſalt teares, could not in any caſe alter <hi>Mountgramets</hi> intent: ſo the one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued ſhe ſhould die, &amp; the other conſtrained to commit the déed, I will reſt, and come to the poynt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calipolis</hi> accompanied with <hi>Anthony,</hi> had not gone paſt a mile out of the Citty, but <hi>Anthony</hi> hammering a thouſand diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paires in his head, (procured by her intended death,) burſt foorth into teares. <hi>Calipolis</hi> turning aſide her head, eſpyed the teares trickling downe his chéeks. Who amazed at the ſight, deſired to know the cauſe. Who fething a heauy ſigh, and wiping away thoſe ſtreames of teares, began as followeth.</p>
            <p>Miſtris (quoth hee) I am forced by nature and loue, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe to you the ſum of my Maiſters ſecrets, which are to this effect. He, eyther ſuſpecting, or told ſome tatling tale touching diſloyalty, a blemiſh to marriage rites, hath ſolemnly ſworne, that nothing ſhould ſerue, nor pardon paſſe, but the loſſe of your life pay raunſome for ſo foule a deede. And none but I, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happieſt of all creatures, am commaunded to be the inſtrument of your death, therefore good Miſtris, quoth hee, forgiue me, though I commit the fact, that am giltleſſe of the fault, <hi>Calipolis</hi> could no longer abide, but burſt foorth into theſe ſpeeches. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>Calipolis,</hi> on whom the ſun of Fortune neuer ſhone, but Plannets ruled by retrogard aſpects. Diſſembling <hi>Ianus,</hi> didſt thou betray me with a <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſe, to mount mee to thy
<pb facs="tcp:11812:11"/> chayre of ſtate, and now diſplayes diſpleaſure with the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſole hate? Wherein did I offend <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> in my conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which hee hath wreſted to diſloyalty? Heauens will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes my giltleſſe hart. I thought that no man lyuing equalled <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> in my harts affection, ſo did I loue him well and faithfully, for which I am rewarded moſt vnthankfully. Cruell Deſtinies, that determines the end of dayes with ſuch reproch. Let any lyuing creature, but once obiect, and ſay I did commit, the leaſt tytle of defamation to my nuptiall rites, and then I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſh death to pay the raunſome of that miſdéed, then pardon in hope of after mends.</p>
            <p>But is it <hi>Mountgramets</hi> minde <hi>Calipolis</hi> ſhould dye? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it was, yet now it may be turned. Hard-harted man, wherein haue I offended thée? in reſembling the conſtant Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, though thou accounteſt me a diſſembling <hi>Demaphou,</hi> or a Wether-cock, that turnes with euery wind. Vnnaturall man, dooſt thou weigh downe my good will with vntimely death, or preſent mee with a ponyard that perfumes thée with Roſes? Whence ſprings theſe frantick ſeats of bedlam iealouſie? Why ſhould he menace death to her that well deſerues? What néeds theſe vaine ambages, it is the Fates decrée, and they haue ſwore my death, the cruell Deſtinies haue cut my twiſted thred, and brought my former bliſſe to fatall bale. Diſſembling fortune, that ſmileſt at my fall.</p>
            <p>After ſhe had vttered theſe playnts, ſhe deſired him to finiſh the end of her dayes. Who hearing the ſwéete ſoule willing to receaue the ſtroke of death, began as followeth. Miſtris, quoth he, ſhould I commit ſo foule a deede, it were death to my ſelfe, the flying fowles will diſcloſe my villany, yea, my guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will bewray my ſelfe. Therefore good Miſtres, quoth he, of two euils the leaſt is to be choſen, alter your attire, change your ſtate, and try your fortune in ſome forraine Land. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Fates being thwarted in theyr déeds, may turne their frownes to a friendly ſmile, and grace you vnexpected fauours. Such is the rigour of my Maiſters ſetled malice, that to craue mercy were booteleſſe, and to ſéeke for lyfe, were labour loſt in
<pb facs="tcp:11812:11"/> vaine. Therefore to eſcape the heauy ſtroke of your vntimely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath, and my diſcharge of promiſe, and alſo diſpleaſure of the Almighty, change your attire, alter your ſtate, become like a Page, to get ſafe paſſage ouer the Sea, ſhroud your life vnder the wings of Fortune, and though it be diſtreſſe, yet account of it aboue an vndeſerued death.</p>
            <p>After hée had vttered theſe ſpéeches, the teares diſtilling like <hi>Nilus</hi> downe her chéekes, and after a thouſand thanks, ſhe gaue him a kindly ſalute, and committed her fortune to the Fates. She had not gone a mile after her departure from <hi>Anthony,</hi> but ſhe framed this wofull farewell.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <head>Calipolis farewell to Fraunce.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>FRaunce with teares adue,</l>
                           <l>Mountgramet is vnkind,</l>
                           <l>I was to him ſo true,</l>
                           <l>as man could wiſh in mind,</l>
                           <l>But now I proue, in vaine I did loue,</l>
                           <l>for nothing I am regarded,</l>
                           <l>Woe is me alas, how comes it to paſſe,</l>
                           <l>my loue ſhould be ſo rewarded.</l>
                           <l>Fond iealous man, whence ſprings this ſame?</l>
                           <l>Thou ſeekes my diſcredit, &amp; ſtaineth my name.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Heauens will witnes aright,</l>
                           <l>I loued Mountgramet ſo,</l>
                           <l>That nothing could content my ſight,</l>
                           <l>but that which he would doe.</l>
                           <l>But all was in vaine though I did remaine,</l>
                           <l>ſo iealous a head had he,</l>
                           <l>That had I beene fleeting, it ſeemes by his greeting</l>
                           <l>he could not more ſuſpected me,</l>
                           <l>Vnnaturall man why dideſt thou ſo</l>
                           <l>Miſtruſt without cauſe, and nothing didſt know?</l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:11812:12"/>
                           <l>Fie on thee falſe in hart.</l>
                           <l>I loued thee ouer-well,</l>
                           <l>Though thou dooſt cauſe my ſmart,</l>
                           <l>and makes my hart to ſwell,</l>
                           <l>Fie on thee froward crabed and vntoward,</l>
                           <l>that condemnes without crime,</l>
                           <l>She needs not to mend, that nere did offend,</l>
                           <l>in all her dayes and time.</l>
                           <l>Vnkind in thy loue I breath thee adew,</l>
                           <l>This hard-harted dealing will cauſe thee rew,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Yeeld Phoebus teares amaine,</l>
                           <l>come groane yee Graces three,</l>
                           <l>The louing wight is ſlaine,</l>
                           <l>in hart the more pitty,</l>
                           <l>Some obſcure cloud, fayre Phoebe ſhroud,</l>
                           <l>whilſt I depart from Fraunce,</l>
                           <l>Be darke the day, that vnſeene I may be,</l>
                           <l>bewayle my haples chaunce.</l>
                           <l>All pleaſures paſt I muſt forſake,</l>
                           <l>All the glories once I did in pleaſure take.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>She hauing ended this Dittie, committed her fortunes to <hi>Neptune,</hi> ſhip and wind ſeruing for the purpoſe, with which ile reſt, and come to King <hi>Lewis,</hi> who being paſſionate fell to theſe ſpeeches. Ah <hi>Lewis,</hi> ouer-cloyed griefes will cauſe thy hart to burſt, hadeſt thou firſt dyed when firſt thou gazedſt on the Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaliſk, then hadſt thou periſhed before deſire begunne, but now begunne I heere expect but death: nay worſe then death. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of that Saint in whom I haue ſhrowded my affection, that Goddeſſe whom I in heart adore. Could I but gayne her loue, then <hi>Lewis</hi> were thriſe bleſſed aboue all, yea, but I feare ſhe wil not loue, why <hi>Lewis</hi> is a King, &amp; therfore may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund. Fooliſh man abolliſh this fond determination, trampell loues branches vnder thy féete, leaſt they ſproute vp to thy heart, bridell thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb facs="tcp:11812:12"/> for entering at the eye, it harbors at the hart, and hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oke good hand-faſt, it indangers the whole body. That <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> tongue cannot preuaile, nor <hi>Circes</hi> charmes, <hi>Calipſoes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntments, <hi>Archimedas</hi> circles, <hi>Rhombus</hi> rifraffe, bee a medicine for that malady. Fond man, whilſt thou ſits drawing of Mathematicall fictions, the enemy ſtands with a ſword at thy breaſt, and he that talketh much, and dooth little, is like to him that ſayles with a ſide winde, and is borne with the tyde to a wrong ſhore.</p>
            <p>After he had bewayled his paſſions, and could not abolliſh that fond determination, hee pulled out a letter, charging his Page to poſte with it vnto <hi>Calipolis,</hi> where nowe ile reſt and come to King <hi>Fredericke,</hi> who had kindled ſuch hote coales, as al the water in the world coulde not quench, who vttered theſe ſpéeches wrapt in a world of woes, conſumed in a Laborinth of cares.</p>
            <p>Poore ſoule, I toſſe, I tumble, too and fro, one while I think on this, another while I pauſe on that, and ſo twixt hope and dread I liue, though liuing die, and loue is the cauſe of this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie. Fickle Fortune, ſtill froward vnto me, deſembling fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors with ſo kinde a friend, fancie is entertained at my hart, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection lodgeth in thys tender breaſt, delayes deludeth mee from my deere delight, and loue is cauſe of all this cruel ſpight. Imps of reuenge, yée fatall ſiſters thrée, come <hi>Atropos</hi> vntwiſt my thread in twayne, and by your Deſtinies come worke mée thys deſpight, robbed of the ſwéet that rauiſhed my ſoule, I ſtarue with <hi>Mydas,</hi> and thirſt with <hi>Tantalus,</hi> burning like the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable flames of <hi>Aetna,</hi> ouerflowing like <hi>Nilus</hi> in thy loue, I ſearch, I ſéeke, and yet I cannot gaine, and loue alas hath wrought mée all this paine.</p>
            <p>Whilſt hee was thus breathing out his paſſions, came the Page with the Letter, who queſtioning with the boy, after cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine communication had, ſhewed King <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Letter, who looking on the ſuperſcription, opened the ſame, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked the ſecrets therein, which tended to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11812:13"/>
                  <head>The Letter.</head>
                  <p>SWéet Goddeſſe of my harts ſole affection, brighter in beau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty then <hi>Auroraes</hi> bluſh that beautifies the ſiluered ſkyes fayrer in glory, then the turkiſh Carbuncle, or the rar ſhyning Chriſtolit, from whoſe inchaunting face a thouſand charmes, deſcends thorowe the imperiall Orb, and makes men liue a ſubiect vnto loue: no ſooner had my eyes beheld Dame Natures workes, and with the Eagle gazed againſt the ſunne, but loue had giuen ſuch a brauado to my breaſt, as nought but death can alter my affection. Therefore know (ſweete Saint) that the ſting of a Hornet is to be healed, a pricke with the bone of a Dolphyn, is healed by muſick, but he that is wounded with the Scorpion, muſt be healed by the ſame. Therefore ſweete, deeme not of my loue otherwiſe then I deſerue, for I haue heard it ſayd, there is more content in a Countrey Cottage, then a Kings Pallace. <hi>Solinus</hi> the Turkiſh Emperor, made more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of a poore milke-mayde, then the King of Hungaries Daughter. <hi>Diogenes</hi> commended one in a home-ſpunne gray gowne, more then one that ſhyned in ſilken robes, alluding to the Lapidarians, that chooſe not ſtones for beauty, but vertue, the Diamond is bright, yet a deadly poyſon, the glorious coate hides the venemous Snake, the gréeneſt trées, the fuller of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpillers, the Baſſaliſke lurketh in the cleareſt fountaine, the ſweeteſt wine the moſt filthy dregs, the fuller of beauty, the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is, the emptier of vertue, reſembling the beautifull Roſes in Barbary, that perriſh in the prime, or the hearb <hi>Soli,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing croped, looſeth both colour and vertue, the apples of <hi>Tantalus,</hi> that touched turne to aſhes.</p>
                  <p>But to be briefe, ſwéete loue, you know my eſtate to be reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, (ſuch is louers content) and if thou haſt reaſon to deeme of ſnow by the whitenes, or trees by the bloſſomes, thou mayſt eaſily perceaue by the furrowes in my face, which deciphers the ſorrowes of my ſoule, that thou art ſhe, yea thou art onely ſhe, is miſtreſſe and commaunder of my heart, my Diadem, and all I
<pb facs="tcp:11812:13"/> haue. Were it to win thy loue and make thee Empreſſe of the world, I would vndertake the taſke with <hi>Alexander.</hi> Thus reſtleſſe flowing in the tempeſtious ſeas of my loue, I reſt at your friendly liking, the procurer of my life, or your deniall the finiſher of dayes.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours for euer, though neuer, Lewis King of Fraunce.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Fredericke</hi> hauing read the Letter, vnderſtood the lines, and marking the meaning of euery minnom, began in this manner, (deliuering the Letter backe to the Page, and commaunding him to make ſpéed.)</p>
            <p>Amorous man, thys kinde writing ſhewes thy interior af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, the painting of theſe fine phraſes, deciphers an inward diſſembling. What, Kings are to gaze at ſtarres, and not to ſtumble on ſtones. Stay <hi>Fredericke,</hi> therein thou pincheſt thy ſelfe by the elbow, <hi>Medium tenere tuiſſimum eſt,</hi> the meane is ſweete melody, ſtrings high ſtretched, eyther ſoone cracke, or quickly grow out of tune. Attempt not with <hi>Phaeton,</hi> leaſt thou drowne with <hi>Icarus,</hi> a homely place harbors more content then a Kings Court, Vertue is not ſhrowded vnder beauties wings, it is often ſhadowed with the home-ſpunne coate. Fonde <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke,</hi> what haſt thou done? eaten with the Deare againſt the winde, or yéelded with the Harts in Calabria, that knowing <hi>Dictanum</hi> poyſon, ſtill bruſe it with greedines, or grazed againſt the bowe till thou art ſtriken with the boult? Haſt thou ſored with the Eagle againſt the Sunne, till thou art dazeled? Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man, thy raſh dooing is more preiudiciall then thy forward affection. Thou haſt made thy friend thy foe, encurred <hi>Lewis</hi> his diſpleaſure, by ouer-looking his ſecrets.</p>
            <p>Whilſt hée was thus ſolitary, vnloding his ſecrets, came the Page back, who brought worde of <hi>Calipolis</hi> death, which heauie tyding was ſuch a corroſiue to <hi>Fredericks</hi> hart, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his pen in hand, after hée had vttered theſe lines folowing,
<pb facs="tcp:11812:14"/> hee framed a mournfull Dittie of her death, and ſo béeing wardly gréeued, he departed from Fraunce.</p>
            <sp>
               <l>Héer's heapes of newes vnto a wounded hart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calipolis,</hi> in whom I ioyed moſt is dead:</l>
               <l>Dead is that ioy wherein I tooke delight,</l>
               <l>Fled is delight, and ſorrow takes the place,</l>
               <l>Sorrow gins to harbor at my hart,</l>
               <l>Hart ſwels, with vnexpected greefes,</l>
               <l>Greefe is begunne, all pleaſure bids adiew.</l>
               <l>Adiew to worlds content on earth,</l>
               <l>Earth, all earthly ioyes are fled my hart,</l>
               <l>And care hath compaſt euery little part.</l>
               <l>And more, to adde greefe vpon gréefe</l>
               <l>Vnto a wofull hart that grones,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt incurred diſpleaſure of thy friend,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> I meane, will ſure reuenge the ſame.</l>
               <l>Fond man, I did preſume a note too hie.</l>
               <l>And if I did, yet <hi>Lewis</hi> doe thou impute</l>
               <l>This fréendles fault to loues blinded folly.</l>
               <l>That may not be, for <hi>Fredericke</hi> did amiſſe,</l>
               <l>And therefore ſhame doth bid mee flie.</l>
               <l>Farewell <hi>Lewis,</hi> though I be forced to ſhunne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fredrick</hi> repents, who firſt the fact begunne.</l>
            </sp>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="acrostic_poem">
                        <head>A mournfull Dittie for the Death of Calipolis.</head>
                        <p>
                           <table>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>C </hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>Come mournfull Muſes ſhed your teares,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>Come grone you Graces three,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>A</hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>And courtly Dames hang downe your heads,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>to mourne amaine with mee.</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>L</hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>Lend Driades boughes, bring pleaſant ſproutes,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>to decke thys Tombe withall.</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>I </hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>In heauenly ſort come Satyrs ſing,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>ſith death this wight did call.</cell>
                              </row>
                              <pb facs="tcp:11812:14"/>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>P </hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>Paint foorth her ſhrine Dianas Nimphes,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>embaulme her with the ſweeteſt flowers,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>O </hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>On euery corner let Poets write theſe words,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>Both Prince and Peſant death deuours.</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>L </hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>Like to the glorious flower that growes</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>all creatures are on earth.</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>I </hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>In cropping it the flower dies,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>thus doe we loſe our breath.</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell rows="2">
                                    <hi>S </hi>
                                 </cell>
                                 <cell>So all things liuing ſoone decayes,</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>But the grace of God doth laſt alwayes.</cell>
                              </row>
                           </table>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Héere will I leaue <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and returne to <hi>Lewis,</hi> who hauing heard newes of the death of that ſweete <hi>Calipolis,</hi> ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into theſe ſpeeches. Vnfortunate <hi>Lewis,</hi> the moſt vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of all men, becauſe more diſtreſſed then any, ſtraine floodes of teares, diſtill them downe thy chéekes, let ſcalding ſighes be portion of ſad lament, thou louedſt her well, and therefore maiſt lament, thou heldeſt her deere, and therefore maiſt thou grieue. Griefes, ſobs, and ſighes compound in one, bewaile her death that now is dead and gone: gone, yea ſhée is gone, and with her goes my ioy, life lingers but a ſpace. Why leytereth death, ſith I deſire to die, for life is irkſome, and I loth it I. Ah now I ſee that I haue often heard, a dog hath his day, tides obſerue time, and all liuing creatures are tyed to a decorum. The Cedar tree is ſhaken with the Northen blaſts, as well as the ſmalleſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſhrubs. The more beautifull flower, ſooneſt eyther parched with Sommers heate, or infected with Caterpillers. The <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> bloſſoms, open with the dewe, and ſhutte with the Sunne, the leaues of Licoris, when it is moſt wetteſt without, is then moſt dryeſt within, the ſmoother ſtreame, the deeper water, a hote ſunne-ſhine, fore-tells a ſhower. The playing of the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, prognoſticates a fatall diſparagement, the pureſt die, the moſt ſubiect to ſtaynes, the brighteſt bloſſome, the ſooneſt blaſted, the ripeſt fruite, the quicklieſt rotten. Euery plant hath his ſpring, and euery Tree is ſubiect to his fall. The Cherry is firſt gréene, but comming to a more gay collour, is ſuffered to grow
<pb facs="tcp:11812:15"/> no longer, the ſmalleſt hayre hath his ſhadow, and the meane ſhrub beareth a ſhade. All trées floriſh not that are grafted in February, ſome perriſh with the froſt in May, and blaſt before they bud, euery thing of what nature ſoeuer, keepes obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of times. Time paſt cannot be recalled backe, ſhee is deade, quoth hee, and there-with gaue a ſigh, with the water ſtealing downe his cheekes. The pride of all that euer Nature made, the beauty of which bright ſhining <hi>Antiphofix,</hi> is ſhadowed, not with obſcure night, but diſmall death.</p>
            <p>Might acts of Chiualrie (quoth he) attaine to recall her to life, or a world of farre-fetched wealth, might preuaile to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the ſame, I would aduaunce my ſhielde, plume my Creſt, comfort my neuer daunted hart, with <hi>Alexander,</hi> eyther to bée Monarch, or turne the world to a ruinated Chaos: otherwiſe, attempt with <hi>Pellecretio</hi> to rippe the bowels of the ſole worlde, from <hi>Archypelligon</hi> right vnder <hi>Capricorne,</hi> to <hi>Cauſaro</hi> fire, burning <hi>Tropica.</hi> Or els, if phiſicke might but be a meanes, I would with <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> ſéeke out the ſence, although ſeauentie ſeauen yéeres I ſtudied for the ſame.</p>
            <p>But all in vaine I breathe theſe ſadde laments, not all the tongues in the world can call the dead to life againe, therefore <hi>Lewis</hi> reſolue thy ſelfe, aſwage thoſe follies loue hath bredde in thy breaſt, and ſith the Fates determined her death, ſend for <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> the actor of ſo foule a deede, comfort thy ſelfe, and cut off his dayes.</p>
            <p>Now will I leaue <hi>Lewis</hi> reſolued to reuenge her death vpon <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> and returne to <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> who hearing it muttered about (as ſuch a tale will flie about a towne, and ring in euery ones eare like a ſaint bell) that the King tooke great diſpleaſure at the death of <hi>Calipolis,</hi> and meant with all ſpeede to ſeaze vpon his goods, and depriue him of his life, which bred ſuch a terror in his hart, that twas no boote to bid him flie, fell into theſe ſpéeches.</p>
            <p>Ah <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> quoth hee, wiping away the teares that guſhed from his eyes, <hi>Aſſes biey danſe aqui fortune chante,</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie is that man on whom Fortune ſmiles, and better vnborne
<pb facs="tcp:11812:15"/> then alwaies to liue in care, ouer-cloyed with griefe. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath of <hi>Calipolis</hi> flieth like winged <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> or Swallowes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſun-ſhine day, and <hi>Lewis</hi> hath vowed my death, whether ſhal I flye? nay if I fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, I looſe my goods, a guilty conſcience doth bewray it ſelfe: but life is déere, therfore farewel all my wealth, and welcome woe begun, ſo farewell <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Paris</hi> thriſe adew. Adue thoſe heapes of gold in which I ioyed moſt, and laſt ſweet friends with whom I vſed to feaſt, adue thoſe floods of teares, I breathe my laſt farewell. Hart ſwells, and ſwelling burſts, &amp; burſting breaths you all a ſad lamenting adue. <hi>Fraunce</hi> in thée I gladly would ſtay, and ſtaied might, had I not beene forlorne, had <hi>Calipolis</hi> liued, then might I haue liued in <hi>France,</hi> but ſhe is dead, and therefore all adiew.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mountgramet</hi> (knowing that tyde ſtayeth no man, and the Marriner that hoyſes not ſayles at a good winde, may be forſt to caſt anchor ere he be aware, then comes an after wiſh,) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently committed the ſequell of his fortune to the ſea, where Ile leaue him, and returne to <hi>Calipolis,</hi> who beeing in the Dezart woods within the Prouince of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> began as followeth.</p>
            <sp>
               <l>Ah <hi>Calipolis,</hi> far from thy friends now breath thy plaints.</l>
               <l>Yée conſtant wiues that loue your huſbands well,</l>
               <l>And dote vpon the fauor of ſo ſweete a man,</l>
               <l>Bedew your cheekes with teares from Chriſtall eyes,</l>
               <l>And let them drop as <hi>Nilus</hi> Egipt ouer-flowes,</l>
               <l>Yee pretty Birds that pleaſure in your mates,</l>
               <l>Let me intreate yée mourne amaine with mee,</l>
               <l>Héeres multitudes of ſilly chattering Fowles,</l>
               <l>Doe hang their heads, and eccho dolefull tunes,</l>
               <l>Ceaſe of ye Compartners of my diſcontent,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calipolis</hi> hath cauſe, and none but ſhee muſt mourne.</l>
               <l>Shall I rehearſe my pleaſure paſt in <hi>Fraunce?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or thinke vpon the gold I harbored in my cheſt?</l>
               <l>No, no, <hi>Calipolis</hi> that addeth ſorrow to a dying ſoule,</l>
               <l>And heapes more griefe vpon a hart that groanes,</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſpeake of pleaſures that enioyeth payne?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11812:16"/>
               <l>Or talke of gold that wants to buy mee foode?</l>
               <l>Ah no, let ſorrow be the ſequill of my tale,</l>
               <l>And mournefull ſighing daily be my ſong,</l>
               <l>Come cruell Fates and cut me ſhort,</l>
               <l>Life is loathſome, and I liue too long.</l>
            </sp>
            <p>
               <hi>Calipolis</hi> had not reſted a while, but Fortune began to ſmile on her to thys effect. <hi>Frederick</hi> King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> being come out of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> paſſing thorowe the woode, was eſpied on <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> attired like a Page, who amazed at the beauty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youth, ſtoode for a ſpace in a dumpe, but at laſt began as followeth.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Frederick.</speaker>
               <l>What wofull wight is that forlorne</l>
               <l>Doth fill my hart with ecchoes of his plaints?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calipolis.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Randall</hi> a haples youth of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Frederick.</speaker>
               <l>It greeues my hart to ſee ſo ſwéet a youth.</l>
               <l>Of age ſo tender, yet ouer-growne with griefe,</l>
               <l>Speake <hi>Randall</hi> whether dooſt thou trauell?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calipolis.</speaker>
               <l>Euen whether my Fortune wills I ſhould.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>The more I gaze, the more I grieue to ſee,</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt face that ere my eyes beheld,</l>
                  <l>Much queſtioning addes greefe vnto his hart,</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Randall,</hi> thou ſhalt hence with mee.</l>
                  <l>Thy beauty bindes my hart to fauour thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Randall,</hi> thou ſhalt be bed-made with my ſelfe.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Randall</hi> turning his head aſide in this manner,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah that ſame newes is worſe then all the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Randall</hi> looke aboue tis beſt.</l>
                  <l>Pardon dread King, I am a poore mans ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Therefore vnfit to be your Highnes bed-mate.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Frederick.</speaker>
               <p>I force not of thy birth, beautie makes thee loued, for wert thou a woman, I would make thée a Queene.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calipolis.</speaker>
               <p>Ah now I doubt I am betraied, dread Soueraigne (quoth ſhe vpon her knees) graunt mee one requeſt, tending to
<pb facs="tcp:11812:16"/> this effect. <hi>Randall</hi> hath vowed till his returne to <hi>Fraunce</hi> neuer to ſleepe but on his mother earth, then grant thys fauour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>acious Prince.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Frede.</speaker>
               <p>The many fauours in thy louely face, hath graft af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ection in my tender hart, that diddſt thou aſke my Diademe, it could not be denyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calipolis.</speaker>
               <p>Then <hi>Randall</hi> is bound to pray for <hi>Fredericks</hi> life.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>After much more prattle had, (which I haue ſhortned, for breuitie ſake) they both departed towards the Daniſh Court, the ioy <hi>Frederick</hi> conceiued, in finding ſo gallant a Youth, I omit to the Readers cenſure, and how Fortune hauing wrapped <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> in the fouldes of her deitie, did highly fauor her, ſhall after follow.</p>
            <p>Now let vs come to <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> who hauing eſcaped the frownes of <hi>Aeolus,</hi> &amp; the dangers of <hi>Neptune,</hi> the raging blaſts of <hi>Boreas,</hi> the Deſtenies ſo plotted his courſe, that intending to haue landed in Spaine, hee was ſet aſhore in <hi>Denmarke.</hi> Then he ſuſpected the Fates had decreed the fall of his fortune, and the end of his dayes, yeelded himſelfe to the remnant of Fortunes pleaſure, beginning in thys manner. I knowe (quoth hee) the Gods are offended with me, for ſo foule a fact, and therefore hath charactered ſome fatall diſparagement, in the furrowes of my face, for when I thinke on that harmleſſe <hi>Calipolis,</hi> a certaine grieuing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh (betwraying a guiltie conſcience) ouer-cleies my feeble hart. I looke like a condemned man at the place of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, my culler changeth to a blood red, for telling the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I conſented to, nay, commaunded, or chiefeſt committed. Therefore <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> content thee with what calamities ſoeuer the Gods croſſe thee withall, for their cruelleſt doome, is thy due deſert, thou haſt doone to death, (with that the teares guſhed out ſo faſt, that he could hardly ſpeake a word) the pryde of all <hi>Dianas</hi> ſprouts. Was ſhée not fayre, as are the Swans that on <hi>Meander</hi> ſwim? was ſhee not louely as faire <hi>Dido,</hi> the <hi>Carthage</hi> Queene? was ſhe not conſtant, as <hi>Silera</hi> was? chaſt as fayre <hi>Diana</hi> was? is ſhe a <hi>Polip</hi> in change? no a Diamond in
<pb facs="tcp:11812:17"/> all her deeds. No reaſon then that ſhe ſhould dye. But fooliſh iealouſie inforced me to the fact, a fact moſt heinous to the world: vnpardonable of Gods, and men, the death of her who alwayes loued thee well, too paſſing well, but that was quite forgot. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious man, me thinks theſe ſilly chattering birds, cryes for reuenge, each buſh that ſhakes dooth make me ſteppe aſide, and ſince the diſmall houre of her vntimely death, <hi>Phoebus</hi> is ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder a cloude, <hi>Sol</hi> denyes her euening ſhine, <hi>Aurora</hi> in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure darknes ſhowes his face, and all things reuerſant turnes to an obſcurity.</p>
            <p>After he had thus bewailed his preſent miſery a ſpace, hee ſhifted his wearied ſteps towards the Daniſh Court, &amp; hauing neyther company, nor hope of good comfort, to driue away bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conceits, he framed this ſorrowfull Sonnet.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="sonnet">
                        <head>The Sonnet.</head>
                        <l>YE wofull wights that ſwimmes in reſtleſſe paine,</l>
                        <l>Yee hapleſſe men that ſorrow doe ſuſtaine,</l>
                        <l>Shedde forth your teares, and mourne a while with mee,</l>
                        <l>Whom ſpightfull Fates hath croſt with cruelty.</l>
                        <l>Sometimes in Fraunce I lyued in great ioy,</l>
                        <l>Nere taſted griefe, nor felt ſuch hard anoy,</l>
                        <l>All things I had that hart could once requeſt,</l>
                        <l>My credit ſprung and floriſhed with the beſt:</l>
                        <l>Till Fortune, Goddeſſe of each ſecrete thought,</l>
                        <l>Within few yeeres thus hatefully hath wrought.</l>
                        <l>For which fact, with bleeding hart I grone.</l>
                        <l>The death of her who now is dead and gone.</l>
                        <l>Fond conceited Iealouſie, an enemy to delight,</l>
                        <l>Was cauſe that wrought on mee this cruell ſpight.</l>
                        <l>I was her death, that loued mee more then life,</l>
                        <l>Conſtant Calipolis, my deere and faithfull wife.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11812:17"/>
                        <l>Hard was my hap to ſeeke her wofull end,</l>
                        <l>That was to me ſo ſweet approued friend.</l>
                        <l>Yee cruell Fates the cauſers of this ill,</l>
                        <l>Come ſpet your ſpight my ſilly hart to kill.</l>
                        <l>If hatefull hell affords more cruell ſmart,</l>
                        <l>Then Death poſſeſſe my inward troubled hart,</l>
                        <l>For better tis that I forth-with ſhould die,</l>
                        <l>Then liue on earth, and want her companie.</l>
                        <l>Vnhappy was the time, the day, the howre,</l>
                        <l>That turn'd my ſweet to ſuch a lothſome ſowre.</l>
                        <l>Well may I wiſh the man to liue in paine</l>
                        <l>Of ceaſeleſſe torments, neuer eaſe to gaine,</l>
                        <l>That firſt by Art preſented to my ſight,</l>
                        <l>The view of that which ſtill afflicts my ſprite.</l>
                        <l>But more accurſed be that caitiue ſlaue,</l>
                        <l>Which hath perform'd the charge I raſhly gaue.</l>
                        <l>And if the Gods haue any plague in ſtore,</l>
                        <l>Neuer yet heard of, or made knowne before,</l>
                        <l>Where-with they meane, to men ſhall be expreſt,</l>
                        <l>How much the fact of murder they deteſt,</l>
                        <l>Let it for vengeance fall vpon his head,</l>
                        <l>That others may by his example dread.</l>
                        <l>Ceaſe, ceaſe Mountgramet, for thy wiſh is vaine,</l>
                        <l>He was thy ſeruant, thou didſt him conſtraine,</l>
                        <l>And cauſeleſſe curſe, like arrowe ſhot vpright</l>
                        <l>Returning downe, on thine owne head will light:</l>
                        <l>Therefore ſith I my ſelfe haue done the wrong,</l>
                        <l>I wiſh reuenge on my commaunding tongue.</l>
                        <l>I wiſh the fiends to vomit vp their fill,</l>
                        <l>And at their pleaſure worke on me their will,</l>
                        <l>Both Fates and fiends full ſore I did offend,</l>
                        <l>In cruell ſort her guiltleſſe life to end.</l>
                        <l>I know twere vaine a pardon for to craue</l>
                        <l>Of all the Gods, which no remorſe will haue.</l>
                        <l>Whilſt here I liue, I looke for nought but paine,</l>
                        <l>And after life in hell for to remaine.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11812:18"/>
                        <l>Where multitudes of wicked murthering wights,</l>
                        <l>Tormented are in damned wofull plights.</l>
                        <l>All pleaſures packe, and welcome woe begun,</l>
                        <l>Sighing ſhall be my ſong, all merry notes are done,</l>
                        <l>And ſtill in teares lament my foule offence,</l>
                        <l>Till Death doe ſtrike, and I muſt needs goe hence.</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Hauing ended this Sonnet, Fortune hauing diſplayed her enſignes, and got the triumph to her owne content, began with a friendly ſmile to chéere a ſorrowfull hart in this ſort. <hi>Calipolis</hi> beeing ſent in her Page attire with certaine Letters concerning the Kings affaires, to one of his Nobility, in making her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, chanced to fixe her eyes vpon this diſtreſſed man <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramet,</hi> whoſe <hi>Atlas</hi> burthen of cares, had altered ſo much hys countenaunce, and on the contrary part, the ſuppoſed death and change of attire, ſo farre altered <hi>Calipolis,</hi> that one knewe not another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calipolis</hi> recalling to minde her owne former calamities, in friendly curteſie gaue him the time of the day, and queſtioned with him ſomwhat merrily of his Country and trauel. Whether he knew the murthering huſband of <hi>Calipolis?</hi> at which words, <hi>Mountgramet</hi> ſuſpecting hee had béene betrayed, thinking life was ſweet, began to check <hi>Calipolis,</hi> calling her an inquiſitiue boy, wiſhing if ſhe would auoyd his diſpleaſure, to be packing, leaſt he furred his Mandilion with a few Lamb-ſkinnes. Then <hi>Calipolis</hi> ſuſpecting him to be ſome ſpye, and calling to mind the credite got if ſhe could conquer him, the feeblenes of the man hartned her to theſe ſpeeches.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calip.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra you muſt with me to the King, ſuſpition ſayes thou art a ſpie, and if thou be not ſuch a man, draw thy weapon for I meane to try thée.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mount.</speaker>
               <p>Youngſtar I defie thée.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calip.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt try me, then after defie mée.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mount.</speaker>
               <p>There lie my weapons, thou haſt conquered me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calip.</speaker>
               <p>Then let me ioy in thy captiuitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:11812:18"/>
               <speaker>Mount.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd let me ioy with gazing on thy beauty, thou ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> whom whilom I loued deere, that were I <hi>Alcides,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dſt conquer me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Calipo.</speaker>
               <p>He dooth ſo néerely reſemble him whom late I loued, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere I hard harted <hi>Scipio,</hi> I muſt fauour him. Captiue I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y hart is ouer-cloyed with greefe, ſtep aſide, and vnlode them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy ſelfe. <hi>Mountgramet</hi> ſtepping aſide, leaning himſelfe vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hady bough, began as followeth.</p>
               <p>Vnfortunate man, I ſee the Deſtinies determines a final end of thy dayes. For when I drew my ſword with intent to ſtrike, a ſodaine conceite preſent, forced me to throw downe my wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, my feeble hart was fully perſwaded it was the very goaſt of <hi>Calipolis,</hi> with that a certaine flood of teares guſhed forth, and finiſhed his tale for a ſpace.</p>
               <p>Then fell <hi>Calipolis</hi> to theſe ſodaine paſſions. Fond <hi>Calipolis,</hi> what fooliſh imaginations haſt thou bred in thy breſt? may not one man be like another. <hi>Mountgramet</hi> liues ſafe and ſecure in Fraunce, &amp; let Fortune ſhow all the authority her deity affords, &amp; ſhe cannot bring her triumph to ſuch effect. Tis but a thought bred in a ſuſpitious hart, vnlikely to be true, becauſe vnlike to be brought to ſuch a purpoſe. But what ſhould one ſay, the Fates are frowning, and their deity is of great force, therfore perſwade thy ſelfe it may be. With that ſhe hung downe her head, and ſaid no more. <hi>Mountgramet</hi> hauing wiped away the teares, began againe to this effect.</p>
               <p>Many trees beare bloſſomes, all beautifull, but yet ſeuerall fruits. Many hear vs be greene that are of ſundry natures. If all things that be of one colour, haue no contrary effect, we ſhould imagine Chalke were Cheefe, but fond in thine opinion, <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> is murthered, and thou art plagued for the martyrdome. The rauening Fowles haue fed their fill on her harmeles fleſh, therefore it cannot be, vnleſſe the angry Fates hath decreed her thirſting goaſt, ſhould in the habite of a Page prognoſticate my preſent fall: reſembling a glorious ſunne-ſhine, that fore-tels a ſtorme, the promiſe of a pardon to a condemned man that is ſure to dye: otherwiſe it cannot be, with that, wringing his hands
<pb facs="tcp:11812:19"/> together, he was ſilent for a ſpace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calipolis,</hi> who all this while had ſtoode in a dump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mountgramet</hi> in a maze as though he had no more to ſaye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in this wiſe: it ſéemes (quoth ſhe) that eyther your griefes began extreame, that you cannot breathe them from the center of y be ſo hart without breaking, or elſe you kéepe a certaine ſhowe of vour ſembling, thinking to delude the time till darke night. Therfor or no if thou hopeſt to attayne fauour a my hands, or liberty for thy life, pluck vp your wearied feete, and trauell away with me as faſt as you can.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mountgramet</hi> was ſo bewitched with the beauty of <hi>Calipolis,</hi> which bred ſuch fond determination in his head, that if ſhe had runne before, he would haue followed, ſo faſt as he might poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Yet before he ſtirred his foote, deſired her of all fauours not to interrupt his amazed melancholy humour with queſtioning. <hi>Calipolis,</hi> who was pricked with the ſame thorne, beeing both bit with one dog, was ſo buſie, hamering her owne late coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that without further intreaty, willingly graunted his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Now are they both wandring towards the Daniſh Court, both of them as buſie as a Bée, tempring a thouſand coniectures in their braines. Not long traueling together, but ſtil they view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed each others countenaunce, without any interrupting of each others gazing, but in fine, they entred the Court, and beeing come to the King, <hi>Calipolis</hi> falling on her knees, after the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of her former meſſage, began in this manner. Dread King, quoth ſhee, meeting this ſtranger by the way, all amort, in pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue paſſion, after certayne communication had, I enquired of his Country, ſuſpecting him a French-man, and ſome ſecret ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foe to your excellency, who preſently offered violent words, and to be briefe, wee buckled together, before any foyle was giuen, he perceauing the firſt attempt of ſo tender a youth, yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe captiue. Thus without ere about I conquered him, whom heere I offer to your royall Maieſty for further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</p>
               <p>May it like your Maieſty, quoth <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> to giue mee
<pb facs="tcp:11812:19"/> liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uncle, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke. The gracious fauours that Nature framed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at the twiſe fayrer then the Sapher or bright ſhining Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>éeking fayre <hi>Luna</hi> in her ſiluer ſhine, or <hi>Auroraes</hi> bluſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mornings breake, <hi>Phoebus</hi> beames in a Sun-ſhyne day, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lamps that glorifies the heauens, ſo neere reſembled my <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>polis,</hi> that to conclude nought but beauty conquered me, and were ſhe aliue, none but ſhee had conquered me. Therefore I perſwade my ſelfe none but her thirſty wandring goaſt hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calipolis</hi> perceauing it was her <hi>Mountgramet,</hi> was ſtrucken in ſuch a ſodaine dumpe, as amazed all the beholders, yet at laſt plucking vp courage replied in this ſort, (vnbutning her Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let ſhowing her pretty paps.) Behold, quoth ſhe, none but thy <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipolis</hi> hath conquered thée. Pardon dread King, I am <hi>Calipolis,</hi> whom Fortune now hath highly fauoured. Thus will I leaue the friendly Reader to imagine the ſodaine ioy and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had betwixt them, and come to <hi>Fredrick,</hi> that foſtered ſo faire a woman almoſt a fortnight, and caught not ſo much as a kiſſe, who raged againſt his ouer-ſight in this ſort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredrick</hi> (quoth hee) heerein, thou haſt reſembled the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Lapidarian, that beholding a precious ſtone, neglecteth time to try the vertue, and ſo caſting it aſide looſeth a great value. But meruaile not, for I haue heard it ſayd, Loue is blind, and therefore can iudge no colours, elſe might outward beauty, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer inward vertue. Fooliſh man that hauing caught a Fowle feathered to thy owne affection, and couldeſt not lay ſalt on her tayle as the ſaying is, but meruaile not, for doubtles ſhe is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored of the Gods, to be a miracle to all the women in the world. Large promiſes, great proteſtations, could not impeache her conſtancy, a meane woman, foſtered ſimple, not Princeſſe like, as her friends were able, and not to be tempted with a Diadem, deſerueth to be canonized in Tables of perpetuity, euer to be reade, and neuer to be raſed out, till all things reuerſant, dye in endles obliuion. So turning himſelfe towards the two ioyfull perſons, thy conſtancy <hi>Calipolis</hi> quoth he, hath purchaſt many fauours at my hand, therefore frolicke with thy huſband, and
<pb facs="tcp:11812:20"/> 
                  <hi>Mountgramet</hi> comfort thy ſuppoſed dead wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Fortune be a meanes of more feruent aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Gods ordayned it for good, and ſith all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> content, though the loſſe of your goods, and the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> griefe for the preſent time, to be playne, I was the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this ill, being enamored of this conſtant Dame, ſhew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in a glaſſe by Magick ſpell, which deciphered nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pretended lyes, becauſe I could not obtayne of her my pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The defamation of her marriage rytes, I can neuer quitta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with amends, your griefes ſuſtayned, I cannot recall, the wel you loſt, ſhall be valued and repayed to you both trebble fold, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> looke what you loſt in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> ſhall be trebble rewarded hée in <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe large promiſes, they yéelded thanks to his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, and reſted at <hi>Fredricks</hi> diſpoſe, where leauing them at their expectation, I end my <hi>Garland of a greene Wit,</hi> garniſhed with ſuch flowers, as my barren Garden affords.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11812:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
